I recommend this bargained property.
我推荐这间便宜的房子
The reason for the price isn't because someone died here, right?
这个价格 不会是因为这里死过人吧？
Right.
对
If you're keeping that information, I'll sue you.
如果你保留这些信息 我会告你
-I want hamburg steak for dinner. -Sure.
-我今晚想吃汉堡排 -没问题
-Okay, I'll see you later. -See you.
-好 那我走了 -再见
Bye.
再见
I will ask you out as I declared.
我要照先前的宣言 向你告白
Please go out with me.
请跟我交往
Good morning.
早安
We need the documents for provisional disposition, right?
今天要先准备假处分所需的文件吧？
Yes.
对
Thank you.
麻烦你了
Sure.
好
This is it.
就是这个
-Oba, good morning. -Good morning.
-大庭 早 -您早
Oh yeah. You're leaving us soon.
对哦 你快要离开我们了
Any requests for your farewell party?
欢送会上想要吃什么？
-Then your special no water curry. -Okay!
-那就所长特制的无水咖喱 -好吧
Without Brazilian enzymes.
不要加巴西酵素
Yeah. I had a feeling that was ruining the dish.
确实 我也觉得那玩意会影响美味
I'm sorry.
不好意思
Come in.
请进
Who's that?
谁啊？
-Ishiko, get ready to go out. -What?
-石子小姐 准备出门了 -什么？
I got a request through a DM on my Twitter account.
我刚刚在推特的私信里接到委托
You can come if you want.
想做的话就一起来吧
You may tag along.
你可以跟着来
You want me to come, right?
你想要我一起去吧？
No. I never said that. You always come anyway.
不是 我才没这么说 反正你每次都会跟来啊
Yeah, sure. I'll come.
好…我会去
A request via DM? What an era we live in.
已经是通过短信进行委托的时代了
-My competence must be-- -We're off!
-我的能力已经广传… -我们出门了
-Please continue with the cleaning up. -See you.
-就麻烦您继续打扫了 -好 慢走
-Come on. Let's go. -Bye.
-好 走吧 -路上小心
-Follow me. -Don't boss me around.
-跟我走吧 -不要对我发号施令
They're starting to act like partners.
开始有好搭档的感觉了
Oh. I meant…
不 那个…
-Nothing romantic. -Oh, I'm not…
-跟恋爱无关 -哦 我不介意…
Right.
好
Now, let me confirm.
那么 让我先确认一下
Mr. Takuma Takanashi. You and your wife Fumika,
高梨拓真先生和夫人文香小姐
moved into this rental apartment a month ago
带着一岁半的双胞胎儿子
along with your one-and-a-half-year-old twin sons.
在一个月前搬进这间分租公寓
You've been busy working at
拓真先生和朋友共同创业
an accounting app company that you launched with your friends,
开发以中小企业为对象的 会计应用程序 公司业务繁忙
while Fumika had to take care of two children by herself
文香小姐必须自己一个人 照顾两个年幼的儿子
and she's shown signs of childcare neurosis.
逐渐有了育儿抑郁的迹象
And two weeks ago, you received a letter in your mailbox.
在此同时 两个星期前 你们在信箱里收到了一封信
After reading that, Fumika has become depressed.
看过那封信之后 文香小姐变得更加忧郁
She's even started to hallucinate and hear things since four days ago.
四天前甚至开始出现 幻觉和幻听的症状
Excuse me.
不好意思
-Everything okay? -Yeah. Sorry.
-还好吗？ -没事 对不起
Here. Come on.
来 快点
If I had known what kind of room this was, I wouldn't have rented it.
早知道是这种房子 我绝对不会租
Excuse me. What do you mean by hallucinations and hearing things?
不好意思 请问所谓的幻觉和幻听是指？
Like she hears someone talking, or feels like someone is there.
她好像听到有人讲话 或是感觉有人在那里
She went to a clinic, but nothing seems to work.
她去看过医生 但状况一直没有改善
She's sleep-deprived from the babies crying and hearing things.
孩子晚上会哭 再加上幻听 她每晚都睡不好
So she often sleeps during the day.
白天常常会昏睡
Ms. Ishiko.
石子小姐
Read it.
读一下
Okay.
好
"Did you know that an elderly died a solitary death in room 506?"
“你们知道506号房 有老人家孤独死去吗？
"The person who lived there after that also left after two months."
之后住进去的人 也只住了两个月就搬走了
"It's a haunted apartment."
那间房子是被诅咒的鬼屋
"I suggest you leave before disaster strikes."
建议你们在灾难发生之前 赶快先搬走”
Um, this was in the mailbox at the entrance?
这封信是放在公寓入口的信箱里吗？
Yes.
对
Well, it's hard to precisely call this a threat at this point.
这个阶段很难明确判定这是恐吓
It'll be difficult for the police to make a case with this.
要让警察采取行动可能也很困难
That's why I need your help.
所以才想找你们帮忙
I want the real estate agent in charge to take responsibility for
居然隐瞒有人在这里过世的消息
hiding the fact that someone had died here.
我想要求拥有这间房子的 不动产公司负起责任
Then, we'll claim the moving expenses and--
那就请他们负担搬家的费用…
And I want to nullify the contract.
还有 要求合约作废
In exchange for no key money and cheaper pricing,
虽然不收礼金 租金也比一般市价便宜
it will result in a penalty fee if we move out within two years.
但如果在两年内搬离 就要付违约金
840,000 yen for six months' worth of rent?
相当于半年的租金 总共是84万日圆？
I can't afford that.
我付不出这么一大笔钱
Alright.
我知道了
Please leave it to me.
交给我吧
-Then, may I explain the fee-- -By the way, um…
-那我跟您说明一下费用… -请问一下…
You said you saw my Twitter. Does that mean you're interested in me?
你说你看了我的推特 是因为对我有兴趣吗？
Um, it was more like,
其实是这样
the lawyer who we've been consulting when we started our business retired.
我们创业时咨询的律师退休了
And when I was looking for someone new, I saw your Twitter.
我在找有没有其他律师时 在推特上看到了你
You posted that you used to work at a major law firm.
你说在大律所工作过
So, I thought I could depend on you.
于是我想你应该可靠
I see. Right.
原来如此 对
You have a good eye.
您很有眼光
You're being loud.
太大声了
MIZU HOME
（瑞房屋）
Therefore, we believe you had the obligation to notify
也就是说 贵公司所有的506号房
that someone had died three years ago in room 506,
三年前曾经有人在里面过世的事情
which is owned by this agency.
应该有义务要告知房客才对
-But-- -It's alright. I'll take over.
-可是… -没关系 我来处理
I'm Muguruma, the CEO.
我是社长六车
Generally, I don't think it's necessary to notify in case of
老人孤独离世 或日常生活中不小心造成的意外死亡
solitary death of an elderly or accidental deaths.
我想的吧
Generally speaking, yes.
一般来说是这样没错
However, in this case,
不过我们确认过这次的状况
the resident's death was confirmed when other residents noticed a strange odor
死者过世好几天之后 附近的居民注意到有怪味
a few days after the death.
这才确认死者身亡
It must've been subject to special cleaning.
当然 房子也一定要做特殊清洁
Under Article 47-1 of the Real Estate Brokerage Act--
根据日本不动产交易业法 第47条第1号…
But we rented it to the next resident
但是我们在租给下一任房客时
after properly notifying them about the death.
有明确告知对方前任房客身亡的事
Why did that person move out after two months?
那位房客为什么 只住了两个月就搬走了？
I'm told it was work-related.
听说是因为工作的关系
Either way, the lease agreement between your agency and Mr. Takanashi
不管怎样 高梨先生 和贵公司签订的不动产租赁合约
stipulates the landlord's liability for non-conformity to the contract.
规定了房东不遵守合约时应负的责任
Property defects include psychological defects, which makes people hesitant to--
物件的瑕疵包括 让人不想居住的心理性瑕疵…
Not only did someone live there after the death,
在有人过世之后 不但有另一名房客住过
we've renovated and renewed the property before renting it to Mr. Takanashi.
在租给高梨先生之前 我们把房子重新装潢 让它焕然一新
What more do you expect us to do?
你们还想要我们怎么做？
Ghosts just aren't convincing enough
拿闹鬼当理由
for it to be called a psychological defect.
说物件有心理性瑕疵 我们也是很困扰的
But--
可是…
If you're dissatisfied,
不服气的话
why don't you tell the court it's a breach of contract because it's haunted?
就拿“因为闹鬼所以违约”为理由 告上法院怎么样？
She's the type I'm not good with.
是我不擅长对付的那种人
Even if we did go to court, if she continues to act defiant,
即使告上法院 对方一直是那种态度的话
it'll take a long time to settle the case.
一定会拖很久才有办法解决
Then, the Takanashi family can't move anywhere.
如此一来 高梨家也没办法搬家
Yeah.
对
We want to help but we can't go to court.
我们想帮忙却又不能告上法院
It's common for lawyers.
真的是律师常见的烦恼
Shall we change our target?
要不要换个目标？
-Find the person who sent that letter… -And claim compensation.
-找出寄那封匿名信的犯人… -然后要求赔偿
Sounds good. Alright!
听起来不错
You're very motivated.
难得看你这么有冲劲
Depending on the result, he may ask us to be their corporate counsel.
因为要是有好的结果 高梨先生或许会聘我为公司法律顾问
You think so?
会吗？
That'll be huge.
很有可能哦
That's true.
的确如此
As the manager of the apartment,
身为管理员
I thought it'd be bad if a strange rumor spread.
我也认为传出这种谣言 对我们这栋公寓来说不是好事
So, I gathered the management association here.
因此才把各位住户代表找过来
He's my lawyer.
这位是律师
I'm Haneoka.
敝姓羽根冈
I'm Ishida, a paralegal.
我是律师助理石田
I'll ask you all directly.
我就单刀直入地问了
Do any of you know who may have sent this letter?
有人知道这封信可能是谁寄的吗？
It was dropped off in the mailbox on August 29th.
这是在8月29日放进信箱的
Then, did you all know that there was a solitary death in room 506?
那么各位知道506号房 曾经有人孤独离世吗？
Are there rumors about ghosts?
真的有闹鬼的传闻吗？
Within the apartment, yes.
公寓里有传闻
Maybe that rumor spread because the last resident moved out quickly.
接下来住进去的人很快就搬走了 或许是因为这样才传开的
Did he move out because of ghosts?
他是因为闹鬼才搬走的吗？
We never really talked.
我们跟他没什么交流
We live next door, but I don't even remember his face.
我们住在隔壁 但我连他长什么样都想不起来
-Can we have his contact-- -Not that.
-可否告诉我们他的联系方式… -不行
I thought so.
说得也是
If the real estate agency won't agree, then I guess…
如果不动产公司不同意 那么…
No, we'll continue to investigate both cases.
不 这两方面我们都会继续调查的
Yes.
对
I'm sorry. Thank you.
不好意思 谢谢你们
You all seemed very close.
感觉大家都跟你很熟
Do you interact with them?
彼此之间经常有互动吗？
Our kids are around the same age, so we go to the park together.
我们的孩子年纪都差不多 会一起去公园玩
My wife was happy that it's a nice place to raise children.
我老婆也很满意 说这里环境好 适合育儿
But I didn't expect this.
没想到会发生这种事
Fumika, he's crying. Can you check on him?
文香 孩子在哭了 可以麻烦你看一下吗？
Fumika?
文香？
I'm sorry. Can we discuss our strategy later over the phone?
不好意思 今后的打算 我再打电话跟你们讨论
When one cries, it wakes the other one.
一个哭了 另一个也会醒过来的
He seems to be having a hard time.
好辛苦
Let's help him somehow.
我们帮他做点什么吧
For the sake of corporate counsel, too.
也是为了成为公司法律顾问
Don't!
不可以
As long as we're getting paid, all clients are equal.
只要拿了律师费 所有委托人都是平等的
-You-- -Let's go.
-你… -回去吧
You do know you're not wearing a watch, right?
你刚刚看了一下手表 但你其实没戴表吧？
Could you stop noticing stuff like that?
你可以不要一直注意这种小事吗？
Now Oba, would you like to say a word?
现在请大庭跟我们说几句话吧？
Sure.
好
The past three months were so fulfilling and it went by so fast.
这三个月我过得非常充实 时间过得非常快
At my previous job, everyone called me slow and inefficient.
在先前的公司 大家都说我动作慢 效率低
But you all say that my work is meticulous and that made me happy.
但在这里大家都说我做事很仔细 我真的很高兴
-Thank you very much! -Nice.
-谢谢各位 -很好
-Good job. -Great job.
-辛苦了 -辛苦你了
-Oh! -Ahh!
-哦 -啊
-Please eat this. -Eat what?
-要请大家吃个东西 -是什么？
-It's eggplant nukazuke. -Eggplant?
-米糠腌水茄子 -水茄子？
Yes, it's a local specialty of Senshu region in Osaka.
对 大阪泉州的地方特产
It's more juicy and has less bitterness compared to normal eggplants.
比起一般的茄子 有更多水分 也比较没那么苦
We don't need the description of the eggplant.
你不需要描述水茄子
-Huh? -So, what about it?
-什么？ -怎么会出现在这里？
My mom is from Senshu and when I went to see her last week…
我妈妈是泉州人 上周我回老家…
That may have sounded like a pun, but it wasn't meant to be.
我不是故意要说 “州”和“周”这两个同音字
-We know. You're being paranoid. -We get it.
-知道啦 你为何那么紧张 -我们知道
It's a thank-you gift from my mom to everyone.
妈妈要我带来给各位 聊表谢意
-It's huge. -You don't want it?
-好大一桶 -你们不要吗？
-Of course we do. -We want it.
-要… -我们要吃
-We should eat it together. -Yes.
-大家一起吃啊 -对
Thank you. Please send our gratitude to her.
谢谢 也请转达我们对她的感谢之意
Sure. There's loads in here. What should I do?
好的 还挺多的 该怎么办？
-Shoko, we have food containers, right? -Yes.
-硝子 有保鲜盒吧？ -有
Let's share it now.
现在就分给大家吧
-Okay. -We'll share it.
-好 -大家分一分吧
-Thank you. -Okay, thanks.
-谢谢 -好 谢谢
Now, let me do it.
现在就来分装
It was an unrequited love, huh?
没有结果的恋情啊？
-Huh?
嗯？
I knew that you liked Shoko.
我知道你喜欢硝子
Well, I'm sure you'll meet someone in your new workplace.
在新的职场我相信你会有新的邂逅
Good luck.
加油
Uh, right…
是…
That's a fat eggplant.
胖嘟嘟的茄子
I'll start drinking.
我要开始喝了
That's a lot.
很多
Huh?
嗯？
What?
什么？
Is your nose that itchy?
鼻子有那么痒吗？
What? It's just…
什么？有一点…
Huh?
什么？
You did? You did it?
这个？你这个了吗？
-So, it's this? -Yes.
-这个了吗？ -对
Argh! Now my nose is starting to itch.
我的鼻子也开始痒起来了
What is it?
怎么回事？
I see.
这样啊
Yes. I asked her out.
对 我告白了
I really appreciate it.
我很感谢你的心意
But can I think about it for a little while?
可以让我稍微考虑一下吗？
I told her that she doesn't need to rush.
我告诉她我会耐心等候
You were talking to her normally for someone who asked her out.
你都跟她告白了 竟然还能这么自然地跟她讲话
I thought she'd feel awkward if I don't.
要是态度改变了的话 石子学姐会感到困扰吧
So, I did my best.
所以我拼命装作没事
If that's the case, you did a good job.
如果是这样的话 你还装得挺像的
The manager called and said we can check the security camera footage.
管理员联络我 说我们可以去看监视器的影片
Thank goodness.
太好了
-We should go today. -Yes.
-今天就赶快去确认 -对
Go ahead.
请接吧
Excuse me.
不好意思
Sure.
不会
Hello.
喂
I'm terribly sorry. I'll make it in the afternoon.
真的很抱歉 我下午一定会到
Yes. Bye.
好 我挂电话了
You seem very busy.
你好像很忙
Well, yeah.
对啊
Have you taken your childcare leave?
孩子出生后 你有请过育婴假吗？
No.
没有
It hasn't been that long since my friends and I launched our company.
我和朋友才刚创业没多久
It's a small company with only seven people.
是一家只有七名员工的小公司
The administration staff is on maternity leave,
处理行政的女性员工请产假了
so it doesn't feel right for me to take mine as well.
要是我也请育婴假 总觉得不太…
But it's your legitimate right.
但这是你的正当权利
The law may be so,
法律规定或许是这样没错
but we can't live on ideals alone.
但现实生活不可能这么理想
If the sales decrease due to my leave, we may not be able to pay our employees.
如果因为我的请假而让业绩下滑 说不定连员工的薪水都会付不出来
So, your wife takes care of the children by herself?
都是夫人在独自照顾小孩吗？
Yes.
对
Originally, we were planning to leave our kids at daycare
其实我老婆也想把孩子送去托儿所
so she could go back to work.
然后重回职场
But there's a long waiting list.
但托儿所一直进不去
So she's raising our two sons the best she can
只能一边等待有人取消
while waiting for a spot to open.
一边每天拼命照顾两个孩子
As I thought.
果然如此
-You're daycare hunting. -Daycare hunting?
-你们在做日托吗？ -托活？
An activity to enroll your children into a licensed daycare center.
设法让孩子进入公立托儿所的活动
Lots of children are on the waiting list.
有太多孩子在等候补了 很难申请
I found out after some research that there are points for daycare hunting.
我稍微调查了一下 才知道托活还要看分数
What's that?
那是什么？
It's an evaluation criteria,
就是评估一个家庭
where they assess if a family truly needs to use the daycare center.
是否真的需要 送孩子去托儿所的判断标准
Such as, if both parents are working full time,
像是夫妻都有全职的工作
or they don't have any relatives nearby.
或是附近没有任何亲戚可以帮忙
It seems higher points are given to those who need more help from daycare centers.
更需要有托儿所帮忙照顾的 分数就会比较高
You get more points if you've used a private daycare center,
如果孩子上过私人托儿所 分数也会比较高
so there are people who do that as a part of their strategy to build a history.
所以也有人会策略性地 先让孩子进私人托儿所来累积资历
Wow, that sounds tough.
太辛苦了吧
And I wanted to be of help,
我想要多少帮点忙
so I've compiled some subsidy programs where you can hire babysitters.
所以整理了可以让你们 雇用保母的补助款和补助制度
Here.
就这样
-This is great. -Good.
-真是帮了大忙 -好
Again…
又来了…
Hello.
喂
Not bad.
做得不错
-Obviously. -That's right.
-明显啊 -是的
Yes.
是
Is Fumika alright?
我老婆没事吧？
My wife and sons are fine.
我老婆和儿子都没事了
Oh, good.
那就好
But she'll be hospitalized for a few days due to severe fatigue.
不过我老婆因为过劳 必须住院几天
But I guess you're lucky it was only a minor fire.
不过 火势很快就扑灭了 也算是不幸中的大幸
I can't believe she dozed off while heating the pot.
居然炉火还开着 就打起瞌睡来
I wanted to help my wife,
我原本是想要帮我老婆的
but I may have ended up making her suffer.
但说不定反而让她更辛苦了
I'll give up.
我决定放弃了
The apartment manager told me
公寓管理员也跟我说
not to make a big deal about the ghost rumor
不要把闹鬼的事情闹大了
because it could affect the property value.
要是房价下跌了该怎么办
There's no reason for you two to be blamed.
你们没道理被逼得这么紧
She's right. We'll make sure to find the person who sent that letter.
就是啊 我们一定会找出寄信人的
Will you be taking care of the boys for the time being?
暂时要由高梨先生 来照顾这两个孩子吗？
I guess so. Since my parents live far away.
我老家很远 也只能这样了
I'll try and find a babysitter.
我去找个保姆
-So, how are things? -Welcome.
-怎么样了？ -欢迎光临
What things?
什么事？
You know, your health.
你的身体状况
I've been feeling better thanks to the medication.
因为在吃药 感觉好多了
They said I'll be fine after the surgery.
动完手术之后 应该就不用担心了
Okay.
好
Well, don't work too hard.
不要太勉强了
So, he asked you out?
听说他跟你表白了？
-Oba told me. -What?
-大庭跟我说的 -什么？
No, no. I've been asking him if he likes you.
不是 我一直问他是不是喜欢你
That's why he told me.
所以他跟我说了
Oh.
哦
It feels weird to pretend not to know when I've been told about it.
我都已经听说了 还要假装不知道 感觉很奇怪
You shouldn't say anything and just keep it inside.
这种事不用说出来 藏在心里就好
Keep it inside. Right. And?
藏在心里 好的 然后呢？
Here you go.
菜来了
-Your karaage. -Thank you.
-这是咖喱炸鸡 -谢谢
Thank you.
谢谢
It's mountains of food wherever we go.
不管去哪间店 食物量都这么多
Let's eat.
我要开动了
You still haven't decided?
你在烦恼要不要答应吗？
I said, don't say anything.
就跟你说 这种事不用说出来
We're partners.
我们不是伙伴吗？
Now you call us partners.
不要在这种时候才说我们是伙伴
But I'm curious.
不过我很好奇
Why do you need to think about it?
我不懂你在烦恼什么？
I'd go out with them if I liked them.
觉得好 就跟对方交往
If not, I won't.
不想要 直接拒绝不就好了
It's not that simple.
才没有那么简单
I'm not sure if my feelings for him are strong enough.
用这种暧昧的心情答应他真的好吗？
Meaning?
什么意思？
There are many things I like about him.
我觉得大庭先生有很多优点
But…
可是…
I don't know if I should be going out with him
我不敢说自己百分之百喜欢他
when I'm not sure if I like him 100 percent.
就这样跟他交往真的好吗？我很疑惑
I think it's against my rules.
这样会违反我的原则吧
You really are hard-headed.
真的很死脑筋
Plus,
而且
the firm is not doing well and I should be focusing on work.
现在律所经营困难 我应该要专心工作才对
So, I doubt having a love life is a good idea.
去谈恋爱真的好吗？
Huh? Is there only one camera at the entrance?
公寓入口只有一台摄像机吗？
Yes.
对
I thought there were two security cameras.
我记得监视器有两台吧
Oh, one of them is fake.
其中一台是假的
Do the residents know that?
住户知道这件事吗？
Yes, I've told them.
我跟大家说明过了
Please let me know when you're done.
你们看完再跟我说
-Yes, thank you. -Thank you very much.
-好 谢谢 -谢谢
On the day the letter was sent,
在信寄出的那一天
this is the only person who put something in the Takanashi family's mailbox.
把东西放进高梨家信箱的 就只有这个人
We can't even tell if it's a man or a woman.
看不出是男是女
Unspecific clothing.
衣服一点特征也没有
But…
不过…
This person entered at an angle as if he or she knew the location
这个人知道监视器的位置 特地以某个角度走进来
of the security camera and left without showing their face.
一直到最后要离开了也没被拍到脸
Normally, if you're trying to avoid two cameras,
一般来说 如果想要避开两台监视器
you wouldn't walk in at this angle.
是不会用这个角度走进来的
This person knew that this camera is fake.
这个人知道这个监视器是假的
Meaning, this person is most likely, a resident of this apartment.
换句话说 这个人是公寓住户的可能性很高
This is Ninzaburo Haneoka.
以上是羽根冈任三郎的推理
What do you think?
怎么样？
Sure.
好
We should check if anyone was behaving differently
为了找出有没有人 出现跟平常不一样的行为
from their usual routine during the week before and after the posting.
我们彻底检查 投信前后一周的住户行动吧
Do we need to go that far?
要做到这种程度吗？
You never know what could be a clue.
说不定会找到什么线索
If we check all the security cameras in the building,
只要检查走廊和电梯等处的监视器
we can find out which room they live in.
就能找出是哪个房间的住户
Let's ask the manager--
我们就请管理员帮忙…
Okay. I'll leave that to you then.
好 那就交给你办
What?
什么？
-I've other things to do. -You're just lazy.
-我还有其他的事情要调查 -你只是嫌麻烦吧
Nope.
才不是
-You're not going anywhere. -Hey…
-我不会让你走的 -等一下…
Oh!
啊！
I'm not falling for that. I'm not a child.
我才不会上当 又不是三岁小孩
Come on. A grown man is trying to get away like this.
配合一下嘛 一个大人都想要用这个方法逃跑了
You said, "get away." Hey!
你承认要逃跑了
Yes?
是谁？
Hello.
你好
Haneo called me to ask if I could help.
羽男先生联络我 问我能不能来帮忙
Um…
那个…
We won't be able to pay you.
我没办法付你打工费用
That's fine.
没关系
Haneo said he'll treat me to a meal.
羽男先生说会请我吃饭
Are you sure?
真的可以吗？
Yes. I'm off work already.
对 我已经下班了
Thank you.
不好意思
Here.
给
Doesn't it bring back memories? Our high school cafeteria.
不会很怀念吗？高中的学生餐厅
Oh! The vending machine.
哦！自动贩卖机里卖
Yes, it was always sold out.
对 这个常常会卖完
You're right.
对的
I bought it the moment I saw this.
我一看到就买了
I appreciate it.
非常感谢
Alright. Shall we start?
好 我们开始吧？
Yes.
好
Let's start from August 28th. The elevator hall footage…
那就先从8月28日开始 检查电梯间的影片…
Oh. So you are actually doing something.
看来你真的在做事
What did you think? Of course I'm working.
你把我当成什么了？我很认真在工作
And you?
你呢？
Huh?
什么？
On the day we interviewed the residents,
我们去公寓打听消息的那一天
Mrs. Tani who lives in room 105 followed us after we left the entrance.
在离开入口大厅时 105号房的谷太太追了出来
Right.
好
But she seemed to have changed her mind and the footage showed her going back.
不过她好像又改变了心意 影片拍到她又折了回去
I got curious about her behavior, so I went to talk to her.
我对她的行为很在意 所以就跑去问她了
She said she saw a suspicious person on August 29th
她说她在8月29日那天 看到形迹可疑的人
and she thought about testifying, but she felt awkward
原本想要提供证词 但又觉得是在出卖其他住户
because it felt like she'd be betraying the residents.
觉得心里不舒服 所以作罢了
And? Did you get her testimony?
所以呢？拿到证词了吗？
Come on, did you?
有没有拿到证词？
Please tell me if you did or not.
请问您拿到证词了吗？
Enough with the faces!
不要再摆出那些表情了
I'll be off.
那我出门了
Okay.
好
Thank you for your help.
不好意思 今天也要麻烦你了
See you later.
慢走
Mrs. Kumakiri.
熊切太太
May we speak with you?
可以跟你说几句话吗？
We think that you're the one who wrote this mysterious letter.
我们怀疑这封匿名信是你写的
The day this letter was posted,
这封信被放进信箱的那一天
someone saw you rushing out of the apartment in a hoodie and trousers,
有人看到你穿着平常不会穿的 连帽衫和长裤
which is not the way you usually dress.
匆匆忙忙走出公寓
It wasn't me.
不是我
If Article 222 of the Penal Code "Intimidation" was committed,
顺带一提 如果刑法第222条恐吓罪成立的话
you may be imprisoned for up to two years or be fined up to 300,000 yen.
可判处两年以下有期徒刑 或是30万日圆以下的罚款
This is an old precedent from 1960.
1960年有一起判例
A person who sent a letter stating, "My condolences for the fire. Be careful."
有个人写信给吵架的对方 “慰问府上火灾 请小心用火”
to someone they were arguing with was actually arrested for intimidation.
结果遭到逮捕 并以恐吓罪遭到起诉
This letter may not be as direct, but it's enough to--
这封信的用词或许没那么直接 但也足以…
Now, now, Mr. Haneoka.
好了…律师
If she tells us the truth, we'll settle this peacefully. Right?
只要她愿意说实话 我们也不会把事情闹大吧？
Well, I guess we could.
就是啊
Was it for daycare hunting?
是为了托活吗？
You were at the childcare support division at the ward office just now.
你刚刚也是去 区公所的育儿支援部门吧
I heard that you haven't been able to go back to work
听说你因为小孩进不了公立托儿所
because there are no spots available at licensed daycares.
一直无法回归职场
From what I've seen in the security camera footage,
我看过监视器视频 你的先生
your husband goes to work early morning and comes home around midnight.
每天很早就出门上班 回到家都接近半夜12点了
He seems to have no weekends off.
周末好像也没有休假
You are practically raising your child on your own.
你只能自己一个人照顾小孩
-So, to enroll your child-- -I'm sorry.
-为了让孩子进托儿所… -对不起
Even if we wanted to enroll in a private daycare center like Mrs. Tani's,
即使想要像谷太太那样 把小孩送进私立托儿所
we can't afford to pay 80,000 yen a month.
我们也付不起一个月八万日圆的费用
Licensed ones are our only option, but there are no spots.
只能送去公立托儿所了 但又一直都进不去
While all this daycare hunting, the Takanashi family moved in.
正在努力找日托时 高梨家就搬了进来
They get more points than me
我只有一个小孩
because I only have one child and they have twins.
高梨家是双胞胎 分数比较高
So, I just…
所以我才…
I'm very sorry.
真的很抱歉
I'll pay the compensation with all I have.
我会尽量支付赔偿费用
Please raise your head.
请把头抬起来
Forget the compensation.
赔偿金就不用了
I am mad, but I also understand the struggle.
我是很生气 但我也知道你有多辛苦
Besides, my wife told me.
而且我老婆之前说过
When she was shopping at the supermarket, the twins started crying.
她去超市买东西的时候 两个孩子突然开始哭了起来
And when she was at a loss,
正当她不知所措的时候
Mrs. Kumakiri came up and said, "Are you alright? I'll carry your stuff."
熊切太太过来问她 “你还好吗？我帮你拿东西”
I heard you helped her.
我听说你帮了她
When she was overwhelmed with raising children
照顾孩子时 一切都不如预期
and nothing was going as planned, Mrs. Kumakiri's words saved her.
正当她快喘不过气的时候 是熊切太太的话救了她
She said that repeatedly.
这件事她说过好几次
I'm sure my wife feels the same way as me.
所以我老婆一定也会这么想的
Thank you for everything.
谢谢你们帮忙
No. It's not over yet.
不 还没结束
If you're not accepting the compensation, let's go back to square one
既然你不要她赔偿 我们就回到原点
and do something about the real estate agency. Okay?
从不动产公司那边着手吧
Mr. Takanashi is getting worn out day by day.
高梨先生越来越憔悴了
I hope we can settle this soon.
真希望能赶快解决
How should we tackle this?
要怎么攻破不动产公司呢？
Good afternoon.
你们好
-Huh? -Oh.
-奇怪？ -哦
So this is what a law firm looks like.
律师律所原来长这样啊
Something wrong?
怎么了吗？
I found a clue to that mysterious letter, so I thought I'd tell you.
我发现了那封匿名信的线索 想要来告诉你们
Um, that's already been resolved.
那件事已经解决了
Really?
这样吗？
Yes. I can't go into details, but it won't happen again.
详情不方便透露 不过应该不会再发生了
Who was it?
犯人是谁？
-No, that's… -Gimme a clue!
-这个… -给点提示嘛
We can't.
没办法
-Not even a clue? -No.
-连提示一下都不行吗？ -对
I see. If it's been solved already, then this is useless.
这样啊 既然解决了 这个就没有用了
The person who lived in room 506 came to pass a circular notice board once.
之前住在506号房的人 拿了传阅板要给我们
And my husband remembered that we have a recording of the intercom.
我老公想起来当时对讲机有录像
Thank you very much.
非常感谢
But it's already resolved, right?
但事情已经解决了吧？
Oh, um.
这个嘛
We'd like to use it to check something else.
我们也在调查其他的事情 这个可以当做参考
I see.
这样啊
What do you know about him?
他是什么样的人呢？
Nothing really.
我也不是很清楚
Sometimes he went out in the morning so I think he was working.
有时候早上会出门 应该是有在工作
But he also seemed to be in pachinko parlors during the day.
不过他也给人一种 白天都泡在小钢珠店里的感觉
Could this be…
这该不会是…
I was thinking the same thing.
我也在想同样的事情
There could be a miracle comeback.
说不定能一举逆转
But we can't find him just with his face.
不过光靠长相也找不到人
Where did I…
我好像在哪里…
Do you know him?
你认识这个人吗？
Thank you for your help.
非常感谢你的帮忙
I think he's found a clue.
看来好像有什么线索了
Dad, konjac shortbread for our guest please!
爸爸 请你拿魔芋酥饼招待客人
-It's okay. -Please excuse me.
-不用了啦 -不好意思 我先走了
Oh, wait…
等一下…
But maybe I should stay and have some.
不然我多少吃一点好了
FUJISAKI CONSTRUCTION
（藤崎工务店）
Wait up!
等我一下
What's this place?
这个地方怎么了？
When I saw that logo on his uniform,
我看到他工作服上的商标
I remembered this car.
想起我看过这辆车
Oh.
哦
I think his name was Kunihisa Murai.
我记得他好像叫村井邦久
Was he working here?
他在这边工作吗？
Yeah, only when he was broke.
只有没钱的时候才会来
He seemed diligent at heart, so--
他还算勤奋 所以…
President! You shouldn't be showing this!
社长 这个不能拿给人家看
We're in an era of compliance today.
这个时代可是很注重隐私的
But they're lawyers. We have to, right?
人家是律师 一定要给对方看的吧？
Not if there's no criminal case!
又不是什么案件 不用啦
Sorry to disturb you.
不好意思 突然来打扰
Thank you very much.
谢谢你们
Excuse us. Thank you.
我们要离开了 谢谢你们
Please excuse us.
我们告辞了
You memorized it already?
你已经记住了吗？
Continue swinging in a figure of eight.
重复这个画数字8的动作
Okay, get ready.
那么 请做好准备
Lift to upper right.
先抬到右上方
Ready.
预备
One, two, three, four,
一、二、三、四
five, six, seven, eight. One more time.
五、六、七、八 再一次
One, two, three…
一、二、三…
Sorry, did I wake you?
抱歉 把你吵醒了吗？
No.
没有
Thanks for everything.
谢谢你做的一切
No worries.
不会
Oh, I have bad news.
有个坏消息
What?
什么事？
The terrible twos may have started.
两岁叛逆期好像开始了
"Let's change your diaper." "No."
“换尿片啦” “不要”
"Let's take a bath." "No."
“来洗澡了” “不要”
So it's started.
开始了啊
Oh.
对了
I'll leave towels and your change of clothes here.
我带了毛巾和换洗衣物 先放在旁边
Yeah. Thanks.
谢谢
You okay?
还好吗？
Excuse me!
有人在吗…
Yes. Oh, hello.
你好…
They're both out of the office right now.
他们两个人现在都出去了
I see.
这样啊
There's something I wanted to tell them about my wife's condition.
我想要跟他们报告一下 我老婆的身体状况
I'm good right now.
现在先不用
Hello.
喂
Can you talk now?
现在可以讲话吗？
-Yes. -Mr. Takanashi came by just now.
-可以 -高梨先生刚刚来过了
Apparently, his wife gets sick due to smells from
他说他老婆闻到 芳香剂和柔软精的味道
air fresheners and fabric softeners.
就会有恶心感
Right.
是
And I had this feeling that maybe his wife--
我突然想到他老婆该不会是…
Sorry, I'll call you back.
抱歉 我再回电给你
Okay.
好的
You're Mr. Murai. Yes?
你是村井先生吧？
We've met Mr. Kunihisa Murai,
我们去见过先前住在那栋公寓
who used to live in room 506 of that apartment.
506号房的村井邦久先生了
He has testified that he's received money from this agency
他提供了证词 说是收了贵公司的钱
and lived in that room for a certain period of time.
在那个房间住了一段时间
That is what is called room laundering.
这就是所谓的“洗屋”
You pay someone to lease a property subject to notification obligation,
对于凶宅等有告知义务的物件 这是一种先请其他人入住
in order to clear that obligation.
然后再租给其他人时 就能摆脱告知义务的手法
We only leased it because he asked us to.
是他说想租 我们才租给他的
Your actions are a breach of duty of disclosure against Mr. Takanashi
你们的行为除了违反 对高梨先生的告知义务
and also possibly fraud since you intentionally covered up
刻意掩盖物件瑕疵再行出租的行为
the defect of a property and still rented it out.
也可能构成诈欺罪
We intend to pursue that point thoroughly.
我们打算针对这点 彻底追究你们的过失
That's not all.
不仅如此
This is the result of Mrs. Fumika Takanashi's allergy test
这是高梨文香小姐 到过敏科接受诊断的结果
and the indoor air environment measurement results of room 506.
以及506号房 室内空气环境检验的结果
We had also carelessly assumed that her parenting neurosis had gotten worse.
我们也一时不察 以为是她的育儿焦虑恶化了
But it became clear that the problem was with that room and not her.
结果并非如此 问题其实出在那间房子
That's how we cut our way in.
我们就从这点切入
After testing the air in room 506, we found out that
在检验506号房的空气质量后 我们发现
the indoor concentration of formaldehyde far exceeds the Ministry of Health's…
室内甲醛浓度 远远超过厚生劳动省的…
…guideline values.
标准值
Furthermore, Mrs. Fumika was diagnosed with sick building syndrome.
此外 文香小姐在接受诊断后 确认她罹患的是…
Meaning, her poor physical condition
病态建筑症候群 换句话说 她入住之后的身体不适
and hallucinations that we thought were brought on by sleep disorders
原先以为是睡眠障碍导致的 幻觉和幻听症状
was actually caused by this.
其实是这个原因造成的
The renovation you did before the Takanashi family moved in was a breach
你们在高梨夫妻入住之前 进行的装潢工程
of the sick building countermeasure under the Building Standard Law.
违反了建筑基准法规定的 病态建筑防范规则
This is clear from the inspection results.
检验结果证明了这一点
Her symptoms are very severe.
而且高梨太太的症状非常严重
She's developed chemical sensitivity. She can't use…
还引发了化学物质过敏 今后…
-…fabric softeners… -…perfume…
-柔软精 -香水
…hair sprays…
美发用品
…and products that contain fragrances…
含有香料的产品都要避免使用
…restricting her daily life.
对生活造成诸多不便
You can't get away with it…
造成这么严重的伤害
…after causing so much damage.
你们难辞其咎
Um--
那个…
From 2005, there's a precedent where the court
2005年有一起判例 因为建筑物内的甲醛浓度
canceled the sales contract and fined a compensation
大幅超过政府的标准 因此法院认定
to an apartment seller for liability for non-conformity
贩卖该公寓的不动产业者违约
because the formaldehyde in the building exceeded the government guidelines.
判决买卖合约解除 并向业者求偿
-The damage in our case-- -Please wait. Let's talk.
-以本案的受害程度来看… -等一下…有话好说嘛
When she flinches, go all out.
对方退缩的话 就一鼓作气
First, we demand to cancel the lease agreement effective immediately.
首先 我们要求立即解除租赁合约
Without the penalty fee, of course. Additionally…
当然无需支付违约金 另外
…you will return the deposit, key money, moving expenses,
押金、礼金、搬家费用 两年份的火灾险
and two years' worth of fire insurance and rent paid in advance.
还有预付的租金都要全额退还
Plus, the medical fee and compensation.
病态建筑症候群的医药费和赔偿金
We assume the fire was due to sleep disorder caused by sick building syndrome.
另外火灾也是因为病态建筑症候群 造成的失眠所导致的
Therefore, we're claiming the repair costs for appliances
保险不理赔的浸水家电修理费用
that weren't covered by insurance and the babysitter fees.
还有高梨家不得不雇用保母的费用 也要请你们一并支付
That's too--
这也太…
It's fine if you decide to decline.
你要拒绝的话也没关系
But in that case, we will file a lawsuit immediately
这样的话 我方会立刻提出诉讼
and file a complaint with the supervisory authorities…
贵公司在不动产交易行为上
…that your firm has committed a serious illegal act…
出现了重大违法行为
…as a real estate brokerage.
我们会向主管机关进行举发
If that happens, worst-case scenario, your license…
这样一来 最严重的情况可能会吊销营业执照
…will be revoked and your firm will suffer a fatal damage.
贵公司将遭受致命的损失
I hope that's alright with you.
这样你也能接受吧
However, if you fulfill the compensation for this case
不过 只要你们履行本案的相关赔偿
and promise to ensure to practice appropriate business from now on,
并承诺今后会彻底改善业务状况
we won't make further demands.
我们就不会再提出更多要求
Fine.
好
We were able to move to an area with a shorter waiting list, so we got in.
我们搬到候补孩子比较少的地方 顺利找到托儿所了
That's great news.
真是太好了
It's all thanks to you two for getting our money back.
这都要感谢两位帮我们把钱拿回来
Oh, not me. It's all him.
我没做什么 都是律师的功劳
Yeah. This is a cool train, huh?
这辆电车很帅吧？
Excuse me. This type is not a train.
不好意思 这不是电车
It's called a diesel railcar.
叫内燃动车
Mommy.
妈妈
-Oh… -I'm sorry.
-是… -不好意思
We were in a railway research club.
我们以前都是铁道研究社的
Oh, right.
这样啊
-Going somewhere? -Okay, let's go over there.
-你要去哪里？ -我们去那边吧
Over there. Come on, let's go.
去那边 来吧 过去那边 走吧…
You dropped it. Hey…
东西掉了…
Seems like she's back to her usual self.
她已经完全恢复成以前的样子了
Taking care of the kids by myself for a few days
那几天我自己一个人照顾小孩
made me realize that I haven't been doing enough.
这才发现到我有太多事情没做好
Up until now, I'd bathe them and leave the rest to my wife.
之前帮小孩洗澡只是带他们进浴缸 其他的都交给老婆处理
But drying them and applying moisturizing cream after the bath…
但我接下来会帮小孩 用毛巾擦干身体 涂润肤乳液
Removing labels when throwing away plastic bottles.
丢塑料瓶时会撕掉标签
I thought little efforts like that could lighten her burden
从这些小地方努力 虽然没办法请育婴假
even if I can't get a childcare leave.
应该多少能减轻我老婆的负担吧
That's a wonderful way to think. Right?
能这样想真是太好了 对吧？
Yes.
对
What you said the other day…
您上次说到
"The law may be so, but we can't live on ideals alone."
“法律规定或许是这样没错 但现实生活不可能这么理想”
It stuck with me.
那句话我一直放在心上
The paternity leave system will start this fall.
今年秋天 产后爸爸育婴假制度 就要开始实施了
But in reality, I thought many people
不过实际上 很多小公司的职员
in small companies may not be able to use it.
应该还是请不了假吧
As someone who practices law, I felt frustrated.
对从事法律工作的人来说 这一点令人沮丧
But you made me feel that if more people think for themselves like you do,
不过 只要更多人 能有跟高梨先生一样的想法
then society could change.
社会就能慢慢改变
I apologize. She can be over-serious.
不好意思 这个人就是太严肃了
-You're creeping him out. -Not at all.
-你吓到人家了 -不会
By the way…
顺便问一下…
How about me?
你觉得我可以吗？
What?
什么？
For your corporate legal counsel.
贵公司的法律顾问
I believe I've done a good job with this case.
这次的工作我自认表现得还不错
Yes. I'm very grateful for that.
我非常感谢
But we're still a small company,
不过我们公司的规模还不大
so maybe when the time comes.
等时机成熟了就会找你
I won't take that as…
我就相信你说的…
just lip service.
不是嘴上说说而已
I'll join my kids now.
我去找他们玩
-What was that smile? -Lip service, obviously.
-他刚刚的笑容是哪一种？ -明显就是嘴上说说而已
Seriously?
不是吧？
You're too loud.
太大声了
Seriously, please be quiet.
请你安静一点 我说真的
Oh.
抱歉
Bye.
再见
Corporate counsel.
顾问律师
Those two were senior and junior in the same school.
那两个人是同校的前后辈
-His wife was his senior. -I see.
-他老婆是他的学姐 -对
He told me how smitten he is with her.
他告诉我他是多么迷恋她
He said at first, he only saw her as a senior.
他说一开始只把她当成学姐
But the more time they spent together,
不过在一起之后 越来越喜欢对方
he fell harder for her and now he can't live without her.
现在没有她就活不下去了
That's something.
很厉害吧
-You know… -Yes?
-你知道… -是
Some people say that
有人说私生活过得充实的话
they can work harder if their personal life is fulfilled.
工作起来也会更加起劲
You said you're worried about the firm,
你说你很担心律所的事情
but you can count on me for that.
不过这件事你就相信我吧
Is this about Mr. Oba?
你是在说大庭先生的事吗？
I'll bring in a request and settle it like I did this time.
我会像这次一样 接到委托 顺利解决的
So, don't worry about that.
所以就不用担心了
Okay.
好
Paternity leave, a system that encourages fathers
为了鼓励男性请育婴假的制度
to take childcare leave, will begin in October.
产后爸爸育婴假 从10月起正式开始实施
In addition to regular childcare leave, it allows them to take
除了一般的育婴假以外 在出生的八周内
up to four weeks off within eight weeks after childbirth.
最多可以请到四周
Alright.
好
Good evening.
-你好
I'm sorry to call you out here.
把你叫出来 不好意思
Oh, it's fine.
不会啦
It's very humid today.
今天好闷
Yes.
对啊
Tomorrow will be sunny too.
明天好像也是晴天
I see.
这样啊
Um…
那个…
About the confession you made to me the other day…
前几天你跟我告白的事…
Yes.
是
It made me happy.
我很高兴
I like how honest you are.
我喜欢你率直的个性
You would clean the areas people won't see
即使没有拜托你打扫
without being asked and you don't claim credit for it.
你也会在注意到的时候 很快把一些小地方都清理干净
Such consideration and modesty are also lovely quality of yours.
而且不会特意邀功 这一点我也觉得很棒
And I think that the way you beat around the bush
在解释事情的时候会有点拐弯抹角
when you explain something shows sincerity.
但我觉得那也是一种真诚的表现
However…
不过…
I wasn't sure if those were good enough reason for me
光凭这些就要决定是否与你交往
to go out with you.
我其实很犹豫
But my feelings for you could build as we spend more time together
不过 在相处的过程中 不断累积情感
and eventually become 100 percent.
慢慢地累积到百分之百
I've begun to think that might be alright too.
我开始觉得这样好像也不错
We may have different views on relationships
我们对交往的定义可能不太一样
and we'd have to talk about that as we go along, but…
不过这一点可以在以后慢慢确认
I'd love to go out with you.
我愿意跟你交往
Thank you very much.
太谢谢你了
-Huh? -Oh, I'm sorry!
-嗯？ -对不起…
-Please forget that happened. -Forget?
-请忘记刚刚发生的事 -忘记？
I mean, it did happen. But…
不 是真的 不过…
My feelings are sincere, but…
我的心意是真的 可是…
please forget it. I'll be careful.
请你先忘记 以后我会注意的
Okay.
好
MY FIRST POST IN A WHILE
（久违的贴文）
Woah…
危险…
Oh…
啊…
I'm sorry. Are you okay?
对不起 没事吧？
"Cho"?
“Cho”？
One more time.
再说一次
CASE 07 CLAIM FOR DAMAGES
（事案07：损害赔偿请求）
Someone broke this mirror.
有人撞坏了他的后视镜
-Do you recognize this person? -I demand compensation!
-你见过这个人吗？ -我要求赔偿
700,000!
70万日圆
-Help! -I thought a lawyer could help!
-救救我！ -我以为律师可以帮忙！
I'm upset about how things turned out.
事情变成这样 我也很难过
I'll allow myself to break my rule just this once.
这次我容许自己打破原则
Subtitle translation by: Aya Kudo
字幕翻译：赤焰